<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title corresp="http://imageofirelande.org">Digital Derricke: a Machine Readable
               Transcription of John Derricke's The Image of Irelande (1581)</title>
            <funder>Freedman Fellows Grant, Case West Reserve University</funder>
            <sponsor><!-- ADD SPONSOR INFORMATION --></sponsor>
            <principal>Andie Silva</principal>
            <principal>Denna Iammarino</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>principal researcher and editor</resp>
               <name corresp="#ASilva">Andie Silvia</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>principal researcher and editor</resp>
               <name corresp="#DIammarino">Denna Iammarino</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>header created by</resp>
               <name corresp="#RParker">Becca Parker</name>
               <name corresp="#LZickel">Lee Zickel</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>transcribed by</resp>
               <name corresp="#ASilva">Andie Silva</name>
               <name corresp="#DIammarino">Denna Iammarino</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher><!-- FIGURE THIS OUT --></publisher>
            <availability>
               <p>Available upon request for teaching and academic purposes only, if distributed
                  with the header information provided.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>

            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The image of Irelande, with a discouerie of vvoodkarne, wherin is moste
                     liuely expressed, the nature, and qualitie of the saied wilde Irishe woodkarne,
                     their notable aptnesse, celeritie, and pronesse to rebellion, and by waie of
                     argumente is manifested their originall, and ofspryng, their descent and
                     pedigree: also their habite and apparell, is there plainly showne. The
                     execrable life, and miserable death of Rorie Roge, that famous archtraitour to
                     God and the croune (otherwise called Rorie Oge) is like wise discribed. Lastlie
                     the commyng in of Thyrlaghe Leonaghe the greate Oneale of Irelande, with the
                     effecte of his submission, to the right honourable Sir Henry Sidney (Lorde
                     Deputie of the saied lande) is thereto adioyned. Made and deuised by Ihon
                     Derricke, anno 1578. and now published and set forthe by the saied authour this
                     present yere of our Lorde 1581. for pleasure and delight of the well disposed
                     reader.</title>
                  <author>Derricke, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] p., [12] plates </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [J. Kingston for] Ihon Daie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut plates have separate title page beginning "A notable discouery .. of
                     the wilde men in Ireland.."--Folger catalogue.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴ b² A-L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacking 12 folding woodcuts with letterpress verses.</note>
                  <!-- FIX THIS NOTE ON FILES WHERE PLATES ARE INCLUDED -->
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>

            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Edinburgh University Library</repository>
                  <idno>De.3.76</idno>
                  <msName>The Image of Irelande, by John Derrick (London, 1581) - Plates</msName>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>TO DO - describe the intellectual content of a manuscript, manuscript part, or
                     other object either as a series of paragraphs or as a series of structured
                     manuscript items</p>
               </msContents>
               <!-- STUFF IN HERE IS STILL DEV MSS
               <physDesc>
                   
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support>
                           <p> Small quarto <material>paper</material> composition-book (<ref>Remley
                                 1994</ref>; <ref>Southall 1964</ref>). </p>
                        </support>
                        <extent> iv + 114 + vi </extent>
                        <foliation>
                           <p>Folios renumbered 1-96 after acquisition by the British Museum. This
                              renumbering begins at f3 and does not include leaves that are blank on
                              both recto and verso (<ref>Remley 1994</ref>; <ref>Southall
                              1964</ref>). Numbers appear in the upper right corner of recto
                              pages.</p>
                        </foliation>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>

               </physDesc>
               <history>

                  <origin>
                     <p>Written in <origPlace>England</origPlace> in the <origDate notAfter="1559"
                           notBefore="1525">earlier half of the 16th century</origDate>.</p>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>
                     <p>Southall (1964) argues that the manuscript was acquired by Henry Howard or
                        Henry Fitzroy in approximately 1532. They later gave the manuscript to Mary
                        Fitzroy (nee Howard) who took it with her when she went to live in Anne
                        Boleyn's household in 1536. Following the death of her husband in 1536, Mary
                        Fitzroy returned to her father's estate, leaving the manuscript with Mary
                        Shelton. Between 1539 and 1540, the manuscript was shared by Mary Fitzroy
                        (who had returned to court in 1539) and Mary Shelton. During 1540, however,
                        the manuscript was in the hands of Margaret Douglas. Between 1541 and 1543,
                        it is likely that the manuscript was in the joint possession of Mary
                        Fitzroy, Mary Shelton, and Margaret Douglas. After 1545, the manuscript was
                        in the hands of Margaret Douglas and later passed into the possession of her
                        son, Henry Stuart, Lord Darnley. Eventually, the manuscript was deposited in
                        Chatsworth House, the seat of the Dukes of Devonshire.</p>
                     <p>The manuscript was part of the Devonshire Collection until it was borrowed
                        by G. F. Nott and sold with Nott's library in 1842.</p>
                     <p>
                        <ref>(Southall 1964)</ref>
                     </p>
                  </provenance>
                  <acquisition>Purchased by the British Museum in 1848 (<ref>Southall
                     1964</ref>).</acquisition>
               </history>
-->
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
      <!-- STUFF IN HERE IS STILL DEV MSS  
      <div type="chunkingShitOut">
      <encodingDesc>

         <projectDesc>
            <p>The project is to transcribe, encode, and publish, for the first time in its
               entirety, the Devonshire MS. (B.L. Addl. 17492) in parallel print and electronic
               editions.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction>
               <p>The transcription is based on two forms of a document. The base-text was a
                  microfilm of the manuscript supplied by the British Library, from which a paper
                  print and scanned images were produced. The initial transcriptions were made with
                  those two forms of the document, but the final transcription was done with
                  reference to the manuscript itself. Two transcriptions were created, in a blind
                  process. Collation of the two proved unfeasible by electronic means, so this was
                  done by eye and hand. Once the two were collated, a good rough draft transcription
                  was produced, and the variants were resolved as far as possible using expanded
                  paper prints with references to the images, as necessary. Remaining areas of
                  uncertainty were resolved with reference to the manuscript. </p>
               <p>As far as is possible, a diplomatic edition is intended, so there is a strong
                  orientation towards the physical appearance of each page, including recording such
                  aspects as indentations, centring, brackets, and spaces. All omissions,
                  truncations, deletions, etc. in the original are retained. Text that is
                  indecipherable is marked by the use of the &lt;gap&gt; element. The choice
                  element, containing &lt;orig&gt; or &lt;sic&gt; paired with &lt;expan&gt; or
                  &lt;corr&gt; marks text that is in some way possibly erroneous, idiosyncratic, or
                  easily misunderstood with a clarification. Not marked are ligatures, dropped
                  &#145;r&#146;, long &#145;s&#146;, situations in which lines are placed over words
                  or letter combinations. </p>
               <p>Punctuation in the copy-text, although minimal, is retained. Most often, a virgule
                  is the only punctuation used. Half-virgules are not distinguished from full
                  virgules. Carets (denoting a correction - often superscript - inserted by a
                  scribe) are included and inverse carets are marked with an editorial note. In one
                  situation, a punctuation mark is used for which there is no ASCII symbol. As a
                  temporary expedient an editorial note and description marks the instance.</p>
            </correction>
            <normalization method="markup">
               <p>Spelling is not modernized. The symbol, that in the early Tudor secretary hand
                  (which Petti calls a Tironian nota &#145;et&#146; - see page 23) denotes 'and' is
                  normalized as an ampersand. The transcription distinguishes between the individual
                  scribe's use of the letters &#145;u&#146; and &#145;v&#146;, &#145;i&#146; and
                  &#145;j&#146;, and &#145;vv&#146; and &#145;w&#146;. Unusual usages are noted. eg.
                  majuscule &#145;s&#146; where miniscule is expected, initial &#145;s&#146; in
                  terminal position. Not marked are: ligatures, dropped &#145;r&#146;, long
                  &#145;s&#146;, situations in which lines are placed over words or letter
                  combinations. For clarity, when a usage is highly unusual, the word is identified
                  with a specialized element tag that gives both the original text as content and a
                  regularized version as an attribute value, using the element &lt;orig&gt; and
                  attributes reg= and resp= within a &lt;choice&gt; element. </p>
               <p>Abbreviations (eg. elided letters) and expansions (brevigraphs and contractions)
                  are marked as such in both their contracted and expanded forms. Words, wordforms,
                  or compounded words in which letters are elided by the scribe are designated as
                  abbreviations and encoded with the element &lt;abbr&gt; and the attribute expan=
                  recording both the construction of the original and the expanded format. Words or
                  characters that indicate that letters have been omitted by the use of scribal
                  marks or superscripted characters, or that are understood to be standard
                  abbreviations for the time, are encoded with the element &lt;expan&gt; and the
                  attribute abbr= giving both the expanded form and a description of the contracted
                  form. Editorial notes further describe especially unusual scribal usages. The
                  expanded form is given in modernized spelling, since spelling was unfixed at the
                  time and several permutations are equally valid. Also, scribes use the same form
                  to indicate one of several possible meanings, therefore the expanded form is based
                  on a study of the context.</p>
               <p>Whatever form is used to describe the abbreviation is less important than
                  consistency in application and availability of the codes used. As a placeholder
                  until such time as entities to describe the forms of brevigraphs are designated or
                  a full description is possible in Unicode, the Renaissance Electronic Text (RET)
                  codes have been used to describe the abbreviation, since they are robust,
                  descriptive, based on scholarly evidence, and available (Lancashire). It has been
                  necessary to extend and adapt those codes, after due consideration of scribal
                  preferences, consultation with respected authorities on early handwriting
                  (Cappelli, Petti), and examination of the context in which a scribe uses a
                  particular abbreviation. (See accompanying file for additions and changes).</p>
               <p>The element &lt;del&gt; is applied to text that is in some way indicated by a
                  scribe to have been cancelled or deleted, with the use of the attribute type= to
                  indicate the nature of the deletion. The most common reason is a
                  &#145;cross-out&#146;, which is a penstroke (or strokes) that have been applied
                  over text, crosswise or slantwise. The element &lt;add&gt; is applied to text that
                  is inserted or added (either at the time by the originating hand, as in the case
                  of deletions and self-corrections or later by an annotating/correcting hand in
                  which case there is an accompanying &lt;handShift/&gt; indication) to text, with
                  place attribute to describe placement, if not inline, and the attribute rend=
                  (rendition) to describe situations of overwriting. In situations where a scribe
                  forms a character and then writes over it or changes it to form a different
                  character, the cancelled character is described as &#145;overwritten&#146; and the
                  replacement character is described as &#145;overwritten.&#146; When a line is
                  deleted or is a false start, the line is not given a line number. Instead, the
                  corresp attribute is used to tie the deletion or fast start to the replacement
                  line.</p>
               <p>Scribal corrections or additions within the body of the text are distinguished
                  from annotations, which are encoded with the element &lt;note&gt; and the
                  attribute type= with a description of &#145;annotation&#146; to distinguish
                  scribal notes from editorial notes, which are encoded with the element
                  &lt;note&gt; and the attribute type= with a description of &#145;editorial.&#146;
                  In addition, scribal annotations carry the attribute place= with a description of
                  their situation on the page, or relative to the poetic unit. The presence of
                  annotations is noted in the &lt;head&gt; section of each &lt;div&gt; and, if the
                  hand is not the main scribal hand, a &lt;handShift/&gt; element marks the shift. </p>
               <p>In some cases, characters are placed superscript to the baseline that may or may
                  not indicate abbreviations. They are not retroactive additions to the text, so
                  much as characters written in a distinctive manner, therefore, the element
                  &lt;c&gt; is used together with an attribute rend= and a description of how/where
                  the character is placed (most often superscript).</p>
               <p>Personal names of historical interest, mostly of poets or scribes, are identified
                  as such and refer back to a &lt;listPerson&gt; item using a key tag. Within the
                  listPerson descriptions, each person is identified with a ref pointer using the
                  Library of Congress Authority number, and a second URI ref to the Dictionary of
                  National Biography. Modern researchers or scholars who are referred to in the
                  text, including the project team, are listed in a second listPerson element, with
                  the attribute of type="modern". When names or initials appear within the text,
                  often as a subscript to an entry (possibly indicating authorship or
                  responsibility), an editorial note gives the probable identification of that
                  individual. Each name so identified is within a &lt;name&gt; element, with the
                  attribute key. In some cases, a name or initial is used to indicate authorship; in
                  those instances, the attribute type="author" was added to the name tag.</p>
               <p>The element &lt;note&gt; is used for additions to the text that are marginal and
                  for editorial notes. They are delineated by first, type (editorial, annotation,
                  scribal), and secondly, place on the page (in the case of an annotation). </p>
               <p>The element &lt;gap&gt; records the (possibly temporary) unavailability of a
                  transcription, implying indecipherability, for one reason or another: faintness,
                  obliteration (for example, by an ink blotch), deletion (when it so thorough that
                  the deleted letters cannot be deciphered), invisibility (when the letters enter
                  the spine of the book, erased, or torn. The extent of the indecipherable section
                  is not recorded. The element &lt;supplied&gt; records instances in which a
                  character is supplied by the editor on reasonable grounds that it exists. The
                  element &lt;unclear&gt; is used to identify a transcription that is difficult to
                  ascertain. The element &#147;damage&#148; is used for occasions where the text has
                  suffered some damage, most usually due to ink blots. The element &lt;space&gt; is
                  used to record deliberate gaps left by the scribes, with attribute of extent, with
                  the value indicating the approximate number of characters or lines. </p>
            </normalization>
            
            <segmentation>
               <p>In line with the orientation toward the physical aspect of the manuscript,
                  graphical and bibliographical descriptions form an important component of the
                  file. For example, we record details of page presentation, such as torn pages and
                  a repaired leaf and we recognize of the former position of a page. For instance,
                  what was once likely to have been the inside front cover, before the manuscript
                  was rebound (at an unknown time) is noted as such. Besides the description of such
                  presentational aspects on a page as centring, indentation, brackets, and spaces,
                  for example, a scribe&#146;s use of facing pages (on which some poems are placed
                  in their entirety) is noted. The element &lt;hi&gt; with the attribute rend=
                  designates letters or passages that are in some way graphically distinct from the
                  text, as in the case of abnormally large or elaborate capital letters or
                  characters that are placed in a supralinear position relative to the baseline, for
                  instance. </p>
               <p>British Library stamps are not recorded, however, the numbering system presumably
                  applied by the library staff, which appears as a nineteenth century inked Arabic
                  numeral on the upper right corner of the recto side of many leaves is used.
                  Another numbering system is visible in some places, but it is not recorded at this
                  time. The British Library numbering system is used as the basis to identify each
                  side of each leaf. For example, the library did not number leaves on which no
                  writing appears, therefore, a number was applied by reference to the number on the
                  recto leaf preceding the unnumbered leaves. Also, the numbers for the verso side
                  of each leaf are derived with reference to the recto designation. </p>
               <p>The text as a whole is divided into segments by the use of specialized element
                  tags that record the division points that mark the boundaries between sections,
                  known as milestone type element tags, with reference to the TEI Guidelines
                  (6.9.3). For example, the point at which the text continues on a different page is
                  marked (&lt;pb/&gt;) with an attribute value n= that gives the number and leaf
                  side of the new page. Similarly, when a scribe divides the text into columns, the
                  point at which a new column begins is marked by a specialized element tag designed
                  for that purpose (&lt;cb/&gt;), with an attribute value of left or right. When a
                  scribe writes a line of text in other than poetic lines wholly contained on one
                  horizontal plane and in non-poetic units, a specialized element tag marks the
                  point at which a new graphical line begins (&lt;lb/&gt;). The exception to this is
                  situations in which the scribe places the last few words or word that complete a
                  poetic line above or below the graphical line before starting a new poetic line.
                  That part of the text is designated as a &lt;seg&gt; (segment), with an attribute
                  value giving its place. </p>
               <p>Despite recognizing divisions into pages, columns, and graphical lines, the
                  principal orientation is into semantic units, poems, generally. The basic unit
                  within the text of the manuscript as a whole is the individual poem (&lt;div&gt;),
                  together with its associated material, such as scribal annotations that appear in
                  proximity to a poem and seem to refer to it. The poetic entity includes some units
                  that are not strictly poems, such as poem fragments, anagram, annotation, figure,
                  epigram, and some collective divisions (&lt;ab&gt; [anonymous block]) in which
                  occur a number of what might be termed miscellaneous graffiti consisting of
                  symbols, initials, words, epigrams, and drawings. Despite the varied nature of the
                  basic division, it is here referred to as a poem.</p>
               <p>Each poem has a descriptive section (&lt;head&gt;) in which the poem is identified
                  as to title (which is the incipit) and information such as whether or not an
                  author has been identified for that poem and how the poem may have originated (as
                  an excerpt or a translation, for instance), along with, as mentioned, editorial
                  notes on the hands and annotations, as well as any descriptive information about
                  the page orientation. Each poem has a unique designator (id=) within the text. (In
                  the title element, abbreviations are silently expanded and capitals are not
                  distinguished for relative prominence.) That designator is composed of the
                  in-house abbreviation for the manuscript (LDev) together with its position within
                  the manuscript from to back, top to bottom, left to right of the manuscript as a
                  whole. For poems that have a standard index designation, that designation (or
                  designations, in the case of multiple designations in various indexes) forms the
                  second part of the unique identifier. The exception to that general rule is made
                  for the poems copied from Thynne's Chaucer, which would otherwise have an unwieldy
                  designator, therefore a shortened title is used instead, comprised of the LDev
                  locator and an abbreviated title. For example, selections from Chaucer’s Troilus
                  and Criseyde are designated as id="LDev00-Troilus." Following is a list of the
                  original long form and the abbreviated versions: <list>
                     <item>LDev047-TP1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev047-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev047.1-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev047.1-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev047.2-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev047.2-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev092-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev092-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev180-TM339-TP333.5-BR666-BR1609.5-BR4217.6-BR1255 is
                        LDev180-Cupid</item>
                     <item>LDev181-TM339-TP333.5-BR666-BR1609.5-BR4217.6-BR1255 is
                        LDev181-Cupid</item>
                     <item>LDev182-TM1389-BR3084-BR1409.3-TP1549 is LDev182-Remedy</item>
                     <item>LDev183-TM517-BR1086-TP529 is LDev183-La_Belle</item>
                     <item>LDev184-TM517-BR1086-TP529 is LDev184-La_Belle</item>
                     <item>LDev185-TM339-TP333.5-BR666-BR1609.5-BR4217.6-BR1255 is
                        LDev185-Cupid</item>
                     <item>LDev186-TM1684-BR3670-TP1940.5 is LDev186-Annelida</item>
                     <item>LDev187-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev187-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev187.5-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev187.5-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev188-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev188-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev189-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev189-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev190-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev190-Troilus</item>
                     <item>LDev191.1-TM1510-BR3327-BR848.5-BR1418.5-BR2577.5-BR1422.1-BR1926.5-TP1702.5
                        is LDev191-1-Troilus</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>The text of the poem itself is contained within a stanza division (or divisions,
                  if there is more than one), using &lt;lg&gt; (linegroup). Each stanza is numbered
                  sequentially within the poem (unless there is only one). The stanza divisions are
                  according to standard indexes and modern editions (if there is such an edition)
                  because scribal practice is highly variable in both the intention to divide the
                  text into stanzas and the method of doing so. For instance, it is not assumed that
                  scribes leave spaces between stanzas. Sometimes there is no indication as to where
                  one stanza ends and another begins. Sometimes scribes indicate internal divisions
                  with marks in the left margins, the use of majuscule characters, spaces between
                  groupings, or by aligning the first line of a stanza to the left compared to the
                  alignment of the other lines of that stanza. The existence and type of stanza
                  marking (or lack thereof) are described in editorial notes. When a scribe&#146;s
                  presentation of stanzaic divisions differs from that given in standard indexes,
                  the situation is recorded in an editorial note. </p>
               <p>Each stanza is divided into poetic lines using &lt;l&gt; (poetic line), each of
                  which is numbered sequentially within the poem in an attribute value n=. Lines
                  that are aborted or deleted by a scribe but that are recognizably part of the poem
                  are numbered with half-numbers that indicate their position in the sequence. Lines
                  that are omitted (according to standard indexes and modern editions) are indicated
                  by a row of hyphens, numbered and noted as omissions. Annotations are included as
                  the content of an element &lt;note&gt; with an attribute type="annotation" to
                  distinguish them from editorial notes that have an attribute type of "editorial"
                  and scribal notes that have an attribute type="scribal". Annotations also have an
                  attribute giving their place relative to the poem. Within annotations, if no line
                  divisions are noted by the use of &lt;seg&gt;, it is to be assumed that the
                  annotation is on one graphical line, unless it is marked as being placed 'inline.'
                  The poetic lines are occasionally segmented to distinguish, for example, resonant
                  phrases and graphically displaced words and phrases (as mentioned earlier). The
                  element &lt;w&gt; (word) is occasionally used as an alternative when one word is
                  involved in the distinction.</p>
               <p>The encoding of witnesses follows the practice of the main text, however, the
                  encoding is somewhat simplified. Only the relevant poems are included.
                  Capitalization, abbreviations, deletions, and annotations are recorded. Each
                  witness manuscript or print source is encoded in a single file, which validates to
                  the DTD of the main document. Each witness file can be considered a satellite to
                  the main document file.</p>
               <p>The header section (which is also simplified) of each witness file includes an
                  index encoded as a &lt;list&gt; of incipits (as they appear in the witness text)
                  arranged alphabetically within a &lt;p&gt; section within a &lt;note&gt; that
                  relates the location of a particular poem instance in the witness to the location
                  within the Devonshire MS., which is repeated in the head section of each division.
                  In addition, each relationship also mentions the other contemporary witnesses to
                  that particular poem as a "See also" section and, when necessary, a designation of
                  how that first line appears in the Devonshire MS, if there are significant
                  differences. The header section includes a detailed description of the original
                  source text used and, in some cases, also includes a description of the source of
                  a modern transcription if that has been used instead, but it does not duplicate
                  the detailed description of encoding practices as is found in the main
                  document.</p>
               <p>The internal structure of each witness file parallels the main file, with a
                  division into a &lt;div&gt; element for each poem, and further divisions into
                  &lt;lg&gt; and &lt;l&gt;. Each poem is given an &lt;id&gt; based on the
                  abbreviation for that particular witness and its position in the sequence of poems
                  transcribed from that witness. For example, AAH01 is the first poem transcribed
                  from the Arundel-Harington MS. witness.</p>
               <p>The type of script is assumed to be Tudor secretary, unless otherwise noted. Any
                  variations are noted in the &lt;head&gt; section of each &lt;div&gt;. The hand
                  that inscribes the poem (or poem fragment, or other type of unit) is identified in
                  the head section of each &lt;div&gt;, as well as that of any annotating hands
                  associated with the poem. Helen Baron's designations of which hands write which
                  parts of the manuscript are generally followed, although when the transcribers
                  differ from her findings, the project's identification is used. The milestone
                  element &lt;handShift/&gt; with the attributes old= and new= demarcates the
                  boundary between hands. Unidentified hands are listed as id=unknown. When a hand's
                  pattern of usage varies, differences are noted. The schematics that will show how
                  each specific hand makes its characters are being assembled as well as notes on
                  each hand's characteristic practices. Ink colour is not recorded, nor is the use
                  of a pencil or charcoal.</p>
            </segmentation>
            <interpretation>
               <p>Unless otherwise noted, responsiblity for all analytical or interpretive material
                  that appears in the editorial notes rests with the editorial team as a whole.</p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <metDecl>
            <p>The rhyme scheme is derived from standard indexes and notes made on any variants from
               that information. It is recorded as an attribute value (@rhyme=) of each &lt;div1&gt;
               unit that is a poem. </p>
         </metDecl>
         <variantEncoding method="location-referenced" location="external"/>
      </encodingDesc></div> 
      
      STILL DEV MSS -->

      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="1525" notAfter="1559">1525-1559 <interp>especially
               mid-1530s</interp></date>
            <rs type="country">England</rs>
         </creation>


         <particDesc>
<!-- I kept this ProjContrib list here, but moved all historical and ficitonal people to the personography -->

            <!-- RJP:2018-06-14: Add new people in alphabetical order by first <forename> element. Refer to http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-person.html for additional elements.-->
            <listPerson type="projectContributors">
               <person xml:id="ASilva" role="editor">
                  <persName><forename>Andie</forename>
                     <surname>Silva</surname></persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="DIammarino" role="editor">
                  <persName><forename>Denna</forename>
                     <surname>Iammarino</surname></persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="LZickel" role="consultant">
                  <persName><forename>Lee</forename>
                     <surname>Zickel</surname></persName>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="RParker" role="consultant">
                  <persName><forename>Rebecca</forename>
                     <surname>Parker</surname></persName>
               </person>

            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <list>
            <item>ADD THINGS HERE (if y'all decide to track changes this way)</item>
            <!--
                   Examples from Devonshire
                   <item>AA: on May 29, 2012, revised the markup for publication</item>
                  <item>CC: on Sept 28, 2011, added the names xml to the teiHeader</item>
                  <item>CC: on Sept 20 and 21, 2011, input Elizabeth Heale's corrections to the
                    transcription</item>
                -->
         </list>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>This is a placeholder file for the complete header information. once the header is
            completed, much of the information in the various lists may be moved to individual
            files.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
