<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="plateDescriptions">
            <list>
               <!-- Use this list to fully describe all the plate images. The ID's are linked with <figure> in each plate -->
               <!-- This essentially just shortens each plate file by referencing this list instead of having it all in each plate's .xml file -->
               <!-- You could always just cut/paste these notes into the <figDesc> of each plate's <figure> as <figDesc>s, but I'd leave it here -->
               <item xml:id="PL1F1_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">A soldier holding a battle-axe hands a spear to an Irish
                     chieftain in full dress, with a page holding the chieftain's horse</note>
                  <note type="secondarySource">"This plate gives a vivid picture of the Woodkarne
                     and their costume" Small, 1883. "An Irish chieftain is represented in full
                     dress, beside him is a man with a battle-axe in his hand, and a boy holding the
                     horse of the chief" Small, 1883. It contains a title page on the left-hand side
                     marking "A notable discovery most lively describing the state and condition of
                     the Wilde men in Ireland, properly called Woodkarne." Names Day's print house
                     at the bottom of the title description.</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL2F2_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">An armed company of the kerne, carrying halberds and
                     pikes and led by a piper, attack and burn a farmhouse and drive off the horses
                     and cattle</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL3F3_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">The most famous plate of the set shows the chief of the
                     Mac Sweynes seated at dinner and being entertained by a bard and a
                     harper</note>
                  <note xml:id="PL3F3_vulgarNote">WRITE something about the _rendition/@rend_ of the
                     couplet (see Plate3 floatingText). Discussion of the content/image should be in
                     other notes. This is just for talking about how the text is turned 90deg and
                     how they are speech bubble equivalents.</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL4F4_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">The Irish chieftain receives the priest's blessing before
                     departing to fight the English, who are shown in full armour</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL5F5_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">The English soldiers return in triumph, carrying severed
                     Irish heads and leading a captive by a halter</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL6F6_EuULdesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">Sir Henry Sidney, Lord-Deputy, accompanied by an armed
                     force, sets out from Dublin Castle for a progress through Ireland</note>
                  <note xml:id="PL6F6_marginNote">WRITE something about the _rendition/@rend_ of the
                     couplet (see Plate6 floatingText).</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL7F7_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">The English army is drawn up for battle, while Sidney
                     himself parleys with a defiant messenger from the Irish</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL8F8_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">Sidney and the English army on the march with standards
                     and trumpets</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL9F9_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">The English army puts the Irish army to flight. The piper
                     is cut down with his pipes beside him</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL10F10_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">Sir Henry Sidney returns in triumph to Dublin Castle and
                     is received by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL11F11_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">Rorie Oge, a wild kerne and a defeated rebel, in the
                     forest with wolves for company</note>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="PL12F12_plateDesc">
                  <note type="EUL_caption">Turlough Lynagh O'Neale and the other kerne kneel to
                     Sidney in submission. In the background Sidney seems to be embracing O'Neale as
                     a noble friend.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
